Guide to the Simon Perchik Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Simon Perchik papers
1942-1998
YCAL MSS 743
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.92
(18 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, printed material, and a videotaped interview, documenting the life and career of American poet Simon Perchik. Correspondence is chiefly professional in nature, consisting of letters from editors, publishers, and other authors, relating to the writings of Simon Perchik and to twentieth-century American poetry generally. Principal correspondents include Elizabeth Press and Edward Butscher. Writings consists of autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of Simon Perchik's poetry and prose, dating from the 1960s to the 1990s.
Perchik, Simon, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Simon Perchik, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 14 (videocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1947-1997. II. Writings, 1968-1998. III. Other Papers, 1942-1995. IV. Manuscript Material Removed from Books, 1979-1998.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, printed material, and a videotaped interview, documenting the life and career of American poet Simon Perchik. Correspondence is chiefly professional in nature, consisting of letters from editors, publishers, and other authors, relating to the writings of Simon Perchik and to twentieth-century American poetry generally. Principal correspondents include Elizabeth Press and Edward Butscher. Writings consists of autograph manuscript and typescript drafts of Simon Perchik's poetry and prose, dating from the 1960s to the 1990s.
Simon Perchik (1923-)
Simon Perchik was born in Paterson, New Jersey, in 1923. After serving as a pilot in the Army Air Corps during the Second World War, he enrolled in New York University, where he received a B.A. in English and an L.L.B. in law. Perchik wrote poetry and practiced law from 1950 to 1980, after which he retired to write full-time. Among Perchik's published collections of poetry are I counted only April (New Rochelle, NY: Elizabeth Press, 1964) and Hands collected: the books of Simon Perchik: poems, 1949-1999 (Columbus, OH: Pavement Saw Press, 2000).
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Videotapes -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Butscher, Edward, 1942-; Perchik, Simon, 1923-; Elizabeth Press
- Correspondence, 1947-1997; Series I; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of professional correspondence with editors, publishers, and authors, relating to the writings of Simon Perchik; also includes some personal correspondence, chiefly with other writers.
  - "A" General, 1961-1991 (Box 1)
  - "B" General, 1967-1997 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Don, 1972-1996 (Box 1)
  - Bergé, Carol, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Burns, Jerry, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Butscher, Edward, 1982-1997; 2 (Box 1)
  - "C" General, 1963-1996 (Box 1)
  - Cavalieri, Grace, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Cuddihy, Michael, undated (Box 1)
  - "D" General, 1968-1996 (Box 1)
  - Dicker, Harold, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Dock, Richard, undated (Box 1)
  - Eckman, Frederick, 1947, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Edgewise Press, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Press, 1960-1996; 12 (Box 1)
  - Emerson, R. W., 1948, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1969-1974 (Box 1)
  - Everett, Graham, 1978, 1990 (Box 1)
  - "F" General, 1967-1998 (Box 1)
  - Fine Madness, 1988, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Forum, 1986, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Frazer, Tony, 1981-1997 (Box 1)
  - The Four Zoas, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Free Lunch, 1990, 1993 (Box 1)
  - "G" General, 1968-1995 (Box 1)
  - Graham, James, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - "H" General, 1947-1998 (Box 1)
  - Hall, Donald, 1992, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Hollins, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Houff, Richard D., 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Hitchroch, George, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Houghton, Tim, 1991-1997 (Box 1)
  - Howell, D. M., 1979 (Box 1)
  - "I" General, 1977, 1993 (Box 1)
  - "J" General, 1991, 1995 (Box 1)
  - "K" General, 1966-1998 (Box 1)
  - Kalamaras, George, 1990, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Keele University, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Kesser, Milton, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - "L" General, 1971-1994 (Box 1)
  - Linwood Publishing, 1983-1998; 2 (Box 1)
  - Lucia, Joe, 1986 (Box 1)
  - "M" General, 1963-1994 (Box 2)
  - Maloney, Dennis, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Mid-American Review, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
  - Millet, John, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Moorhead, Andrea, 1984-1997; 3 (Box 2)
  - "N" General, 1964-1996 (Box 2)
  - Nadjari, Maurice, 1975, 1977 (Box 2)
  - University of Nebraska, 1986, 1991 (Box 2)
  - The New Yorker, 1990-1994 (Box 2)
  - "O" General, 1970-1996 (Box 2)
  - Oasis Books, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - "P" General, 1951-1997 (Box 2)
  - Parlatore, Anselm, 1973-1992; 3 (Box 2)
  - Perchik, Simon, outgoing, 1951-1994 (Box 2)
  - Peters, Bob, 1989-1997 (Box 2)
  - Pierce, John, 1990-1998; 4 (Box 2)
  - Practices of the Wind, 1986-1991 (Box 2)
  - The Quarterly, 1987 (Box 2)
  - "R" General, 1976-1992 (Box 2)
  - Rago, Henry, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Rosenburg, Liz, 1986-1997 (Box 2)
  - Rosten, Norman, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Rottkamp, Tracy Lyn, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
  - "S" General, 1969-1991 (Box 2)
  - Scarecrow Press, 1984-1993 (Box 2)
  - South Dakota Review, 1968-1989 (Box 2)
  - Southwest Review, 1969, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Stepanchev, Stephen, 1976-1991 (Box 2)
  - Stock, Robert, 1972-1978 (Box 2)
  - Stride Publications, 1990, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Sward, Bob, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - "T" General, 1951-1995 (Box 2)
  - "U" General, 1974, 1991 (Box 2)
  - "V" General, 1963, 1979 (Box 2)
  - "W" General, 1980-1991 (Box 2)
  - Wabash College, 1974-1982 (Box 2)
  - Webb, John, 1961-1997 (Box 2)
  - West Hills Review, 1986, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Wisconsin University, 1986, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Wolf, Steppen, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Wright State University, 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - General "Y", 1977 (Box 2)
  - General "Z", 1984 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified correspondence, 1951-1998; 19 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1968-1998; Series II; 11; (11 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings of Simon Perchik and Writings of Others.
  The series consists of typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, unless otherwise indicated.
  - Writings of Simon Perchik
    Arranged alphabetically by title, with some unarranged material interfiled. This arrangement reflects the order in which the material was received by the library.
    - April Poems, 1984; 2 (Box 3)
    - Both Hands Screaming, 1975-1979; 2 (Box 3)
    - "Civilization Depends on Five Humanists," newspaper article, 1981 July (Box 3)
    - The Club Fits Either Hand, 1977; 2 (Box 3)
    - "D" Poems, 1995-1996; 15 (Box 3)
    - "D" Poems (continued), 1997-1998; 16 (Box 4)
    - Untitled poems, 1992; 2 (Box 4)
    - December Poems, 1983; 3 (Box 5)
    - The Eleventh Muse, review, 1990 (Box 5)
    - "Elie Wiesel", 1986 (Box 5)
    - The Emptiness Between My Hands, 1992-1995; 2 (Box 5)
    - The Family of Man, 1983-1991, undated; 14 (Box 5)
    - The Family of Man, 1984-1985; 14 (Box 6)
    - The Family of Man, 1985-1987; 15 (Box 7)
    - The Family of Man, 1987-1988; 17 (Box 8)
    - The Family of Man, 1988-1990; 18 (Box 9)
    - The Family of Man, 1990-1991; 17 (Box 10)
    - The Gandolf Poems, 1987-1990 (Box 11)
    - "For Lovers", 1990 March 1 (Box 11)
    - Hands You Are Secretly Wearing, review, undated (Box 11)
    - Hauppauge Tales, 1978 (Box 11)
    - I Counted Only April, 1964; 2 (Box 11)
    - "In A Throwaway Age, A Throwaway Country?", newspaper article, 1979 (Box 11)
    - "Ironwood", undated (Box 11)
    - The January Poems, 1981 (Box 11)
    - July Poems, 1996 (Box 11)
    - Letters To The Dead, review, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
    - Mr. Lucky, undated (Box 11)
    - "Magic, Illusion And Other Realities", undated (Box 11)
    - The March Poems, 1993 (Box 11)
    - "The Mask A Trigger", 1973 (Box 11)
    - The Milton Poems, 1992-1994; 5 (Box 11)
    - The New Vision, 1993; 3 (Box 11)
    - "One Man's Protest", 1973 (Box 11)
    - "157", undated (Box 11)
    - "A Poetry Primer", undated (Box 11)
    - The Ramesh Poems, 1992 (Box 11)
    - "The Recitation", undated; 4 (Box 11)
    - Redeeming The Wings, review, 1991 (Box 11)
    - "First and Alone," review, 1987 (Box 11)
    - The Snowcat Poems, 1980-1981; 4 (Box 11)
    - These Hands Filled With Numbness, 1996; 3 (Box 12)
    - "It didn't take long after watching 'The Hamptons' on ABC...", 1983 (Box 12)
    - Twenty Years of Hands, review, undated (Box 12)
    - Weston, 1993-1994; 16 (Box 12)
    - Which Hand Holds the Brother, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
    - The Gandolf Poems, 1987-1993, undated (Box 13)
    - White Pine Poems, undated (Box 13)
    - Who Can Touch These Knots, 1986; 2 (Box 13)
    - Untitled poems, 1981-1993; 7 (Box 13)
  - Writings of Others
    Not arranged in any particular order.
    - Unidentified author, undated (Box 13)
    - Poems from The Christian Science Monitor, undated (Box 13)
    - James Weil of Elizabeth Press, 1968, undated (Box 13)
    - Rossetti's Adventure in Rubble Land, undated (Box 13)
    - Writing by Allen Planz, undated (Box 13)
- Other Papers, 1942-1995; Series III; 0.29; (2 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Other papers include clippings and other printed material, personal documents of Simon Perchik, and a videotaped interview with Simon Perchik.
  The videotaped interview is stored in box 14 and is considered restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 14 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Images of Simon Perchik printed in newspapers, 1978-1993; 5 (Box 13)
  - Photographs of Simon Perchik and others, 1980s, undated; 3 (Box 13)
  - Clippings relating to Simon Perchik, 1972-1995; 29 (Box 13)
  - "Interview with Simon Perchik by David Baratier," printout, undated (Box 13)
  - Review of Robert Long's What It Is, undated (Box 13)
  - Bat-Mitzvah Reception booklet, Stephanie Barri Enis, 1978 (Box 13)
  - Legal documents, 1966-1975 (Box 13)
  - Library card, 1952 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous; clippings and notes, undated; 2 (Box 13)
  - Resume, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Promotional pamphlets and ephemera relating to Simon Perchik, 1988-1993 (Box 13)
  - Eastside High School Yearbook, Paterson, NJ, 1942 January (Box 13)
  - "Ideas and Images -- An Interview with Simon Perchik", undated; 1; 00:29:33 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002091243262)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Ideas and Images - An Interview with Simon Perchik", undated; 1; 00:29:31 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002091243270)
  - Mississippi Mud magazines, 1990-1994; 3 (Box 15)
  - Posters for appearances by Simon Perchik, and "The King Saw Butterflies...", 1983, undated (Box 16 (Broadside))
- Manuscript Material Removed from Books, 1979-1998; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Notes, and Printed Material.
  Many of Simon Perchik's books were received with this collection, and some books contained letters, notes, or printed material laid in. Series IV consists of papers that were removed from Simon Perchik's books after they were acquired by the library.
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 86
  - Correspondence and Notes
    - Bixby, Robert, 1995 (Box 17)
    - Boatright, Phillip, 1981 April (Box 17)
    - Brady, Steven, 1982 November 23 (Box 17)
    - Britt, Alan, undated (Box 17)
    - Bogg Magazine, undated (Box 17)
    - Calero, Fred, undated (Box 17)
    - Coleman, Jen, undated (Box 17)
    - Dorbin, Sandy, 1975 August 6 (Box 17)
    - Fahey, William A., 1987 May 27 (Box 17)
    - Flam, Eli, 1996 July 20 (Box 17)
    - Fraticelli, Marc, 1979 June (Box 17)
    - Gentry, W. F., 1993 December 3 (Box 17)
    - Greene, David L., 1994 May 25 (Box 17)
    - Harchick, John W., undated (Box 17)
    - Harcourt, Joan, 1994 May 3 (Box 17)
    - Johnson, Gretchen, 1985 December 24 (Box 17)
    - Joselow, Beth, 1994 February 25 (Box 17)
    - Kat, undated (Box 17)
    - Kelly, Jeffrey, 1982 April 3 (Box 17)
    - Kessler, Milton, undated (Box 17)
    - Miller, Kay, 1991 January 19 (Box 17)
    - Milton, John R., 1987 April 27 (Box 17)
    - Moorhead, Robert, 1990? (Box 17)
    - Neyssen, Grace J., undated (Box 17)
    - Nielsen, Dan, 1994 May 22 (Box 17)
    - Penney, Darby / The Snail's Pace Review, 1992 July (Box 17)
    - Pierce, John, undated (Box 17)
    - Quesnel, Carl, 1991 February 19 (Box 17)
    - Rayher, Edward, undated (Box 17)
    - Robinson, Ian, 1986 December 22 (Box 17)
    - Salmon Magazine, 1992 November (Box 17)
    - Sawyer, Larry, undated (Box 17)
    - Summers, Anthony J., 1983 December 12 (Box 17)
    - Tantra Press, undated (Box 17)
    - Thomas, George, undated (Box 17)
    - Whitehead, Gary J., 1996 June 3 (Box 17)
    - Winson, Suzi, 1997 August 26 (Box 17)
    - Worman, Natalie, undated (Box 17)
    - Zeppa, Mary, 1993 May 17 (Box 17)
  - Printed Material
    - Magazines and clippings, 1980-1997, undated; 9 (Box 17)
    - Magazines, 1995-1998, undated; 3 (Box 18)